<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Pole-Vault | Vaulting For Mu]]></title>
  <link href="http://bschreck.github.io/blog/categories/pole-vault/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bschreck.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-09T14:47:51-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://bschreck.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ben Schreck]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[benjaminschreck93@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yes]]></title>
    <link href="http://bschreck.github.io/blog/2014/02/09/yes/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-09T14:35:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bschreck.github.io/blog/2014/02/09/yes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m about to trivialize 7 years of mental struggle and anguish in my life into a single idea, and basically a single word. This idea is that we all have unique control over our minds, and over the path that we choose to take in this world. That with training, determination, and belief we can reach the center of our own beings, and make a decision on our own, without external influence. That we have &ldquo;free will&rdquo;.</p>

<p>For pole vault, that we can turn on all the green lights and say the word &ldquo;yes&rdquo; whenever we want to. Whether or not we actually have the power to make these decisions is irrelevant. What matters is that we believe wholeheartedly in the decision we make. That when we say &ldquo;yes, I can pole vault and I can pole vault well whenever I want to, and whenever I want to is all the time, regardless of extraneous external sensory input that act to tell me otherwise&rdquo;, we truly believe that is the case. It&rsquo;s not something we come to in our rational mind that may be sidestepped by stronger parts of the brain like the places where fear and other emotions live. To actually make a decision, we need to let it envelop our entire being. To turn on all the green lights, and unplug all the red lights.</p>

<p>This is one of the hardest things to do in life, because it involves absolute control and belief in that control over our minds. That is where the complications arise, and why it took me 7 years to arrive at this point.</p>

<p>But once here, we realize that given enough time, we can do anything.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Last Obligatory No-Height]]></title>
    <link href="http://bschreck.github.io/blog/2014/01/13/the-last-obligatory-no-height/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-13T13:40:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bschreck.github.io/blog/2014/01/13/the-last-obligatory-no-height</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My first real meet of the season ended in a no-height. However, this was unlike any no-heights committed before. It was almost like it needed to happen- like I subconsciously made it happen.</p>

<p>Everything that could have gone wrong externally did, short of a serious injury. I forgot the specific pole I needed to start with; I planted weird in warm ups and slipped off the pole while it was still bent in the air; I kept cutting my hand open and bleeding; a teammate knocked me on the head with a pole; I had to wait over an hour before I entered the competition, etc.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>However, none of this was able to penetrate my skull. I was mentally prepared to vault well throughout, without a single misstep. I was actually happy that all these things were happening because it would present me a challenging situation to practice my mental game, at a meet that didn&rsquo;t really matter. I was happy that I got to go up two poles, because I really wanted to get on the bigger one, even
though I wasn&rsquo;t ready for it. Plus, I didn&rsquo;t waste any jumps all meet. Every jump was an attempt, no matter how crappy it was.</p>

<p>It just turned out that the smaller pole was too small, and the bigger pole was too big. If I had come in 6" higher I probably would have made the height, but we couldn&rsquo;t see that at the time. When it was over after my third attempt, there was only mild frustration that lasted less than a minute. I knew I had done everything I could have done at the meet, and I could focus on the positives. Like the fact that I&rsquo;ll never forget a pole again, and that any slight tweaks to initi conditions would have let me win the meet.</p>

<p>So I&rsquo;m not afraid of any aspect of vaulting anymore. I&rsquo;ve proved to myself that I can jump what I&rsquo;ve known I theoretically could for years. And now it&rsquo;s time to start having some fun.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[About the Name]]></title>
    <link href="http://bschreck.github.io/blog/2014/01/13/about-the-name/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-13T13:13:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bschreck.github.io/blog/2014/01/13/about-the-name</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Mu is an ancient Zen concept that means “unasking a question”. It is the third answer to a yes or no question. However, it’s also understood in a broader context, representing the point at which opposites intersect or the fundamental meaning behind paradoxes. It’s best understood through Zen koans— traditional Zen stories that attempt to reveal the underlying nature of the universe through odd, simple, nonsensical stories.</p>

<p>Here’s an example:</p>

<!-- more -->


<blockquote><p>Joshu began the study of Zen when he was sixty years old and continued until he was eighty, when he realized Zen. He taught from the age of eighty until he was one hundred and twenty.</p>

<p>A student once asked him: &lsquo;If I haven’t anything in my mind, what shall I do?&rsquo;</p>

<p>Joshu replied: &lsquo;Throw it out.&rsquo;</p>

<p>&lsquo;But if I haven’t anything, how can I throw it out?&rsquo; continued the questioner.</p>

<p>‘Well,&lsquo; said Joshu, 'then carry it out.’ “</p></blockquote>

<p>Reading this as a simple parable makes no sense, and that’s the point. It is supposed to stimulate thought about the vary nature of paradox. The next logical question you should have in your mind is, “What doers this mu nonsense have to do with pole vaulting?” Well that would also be hard to just explain logically. I’ll quote one more story here, and allow you to try to understand this question by gradually reading through and following my journey as I blog about it.</p>

<p>This is my favorite Zen quote, written by a Japanese Zen master in the middle of the 20th century:</p>

<blockquote><p>To realize Zen one has to pass through the barrier of the patriarchs. Enlightenment always comes after the road of thinking is blocked. If you do not pass the barrier of the patriarchs or if your thinking road is not blocked, whatever you think, whatever you do, is like a tangling ghost. You may ask: &lsquo;What is a barrier of a patriarch?’ This one word, ‘MU’, is it.</p>

<p>This is the barrier of Zen. If you pass through it, you will see Joshu face to face. Then you can work hand in hand with the whole line of patriarchs. Is this not a pleasant thing to do?</p>

<p>If you want to pass this barrier, you must work through every bone in your body, through every pore of your skin, filled with this question: ‘What is ‘MU’?’ and carry it day and night. Do not believe it is the common negative symbol meaning nothing. It is not nothingness, the opposite of existence. If you really want to pass this barrier you should feel like drinking a hot iron ball that you can neither swallow nor spit out.</p>

<p>Then your previous lesser knowledge disappears. As a fruit ripening in season, your subjectivity and objectivity naturally become one. It is like a dumb man who has had a dream. He knows about it but he cannot tell it.</p>

<p>When he enters this condition his ego-shell is crushed and he can shake the heaven and move the earth. He is like a great warrior with a sharp sword. If a Buddha stands in his way, he will cut him down; if a patriarch offer him any obstacle, he will kill him; and he will be free in his way of birth and death. He can enter any world as if it were his own playground. I will tell you how to do this with this koan:</p>

<p>Just concentrate your whole energy into this MU, and do not allow any discontinuation. When you enter this MU and there is no discontinuation, your attainment will be as a candle burning and illuminating the whole universe.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taking a Step Back for Summer]]></title>
    <link href="http://bschreck.github.io/blog/2013/05/30/taking-a-step-back-for-summer/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-30T14:52:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bschreck.github.io/blog/2013/05/30/taking-a-step-back-for-summer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Now I am removed from the intensity of MIT and pole vault. Flying to San Francisco and focusing on new things allows me to step back and review what I’ve written and where I am at right now. More than almost any other point in my life- I am content. Not entirely so, but enough so that I don’t need to constantly think of the things I am not doing. I am okay with going to work for a good portion of the day, and spending time commuting on a train, and then working out, eating dinner, and going to bed. There are definitely some things I want to do to better myself, but they mostly involve talking to girls. In fact I would be entirely content this summer if all I did was work, work out a lot, and talk to lots of girls.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This is good because my mind is relaxed and not constantly struggling to visualize the perfect vault and the perfect state I need to be in to vault. That was a necessary, but off-the-mark consequence of searching deep inside my mind for answers and for tools to better myself. Inwardly, I made great strides this year, and it was almost enough to outwardly show. However, I ended the season with an exhausted mind- which is clearly not a healthy mind. Why was it exhausted? I spent tons of energy expelling negative thoughts, trying to get into the right state of mind, and developing good habits. While I was successful, I needed more time than I had to digest the thoughts and let them become a part of me so it wasn’t a chore to bring them out. The times when I found myself most “in the zone”, and able to pole vault, were when I was completely relaxed, happy, and confident. Unfortunately, it was difficult to fall into this state whenever I wanted to, and as a consequence I was still inconsistent towards the end. I needed more time. I know now what it feels like to take off, and I know that my mind knows it can do it, and how to do it, and so I will not have to wrestle with it every day. I will be able to just flow, and let my unconscious take care of the work. There are no more demons hidden deep within my mind that I need to be scared of. I have found all of them. I know what they look like, what they feed off of, and how to deal with them. I get a fresh start.</p>

<p>This summer, I will get healthy, get strong, get relaxed, get confident, get rested, and get ready. I don’t need to put a lot of energy into the mental game because I have already won it, and I both already have the habits needed to carry me forward, and the wherewithal to create all the habits I need. I will take a few weeks in the middle of the summer to do one last soul-searching and let the last few stragglers of another time out of the gates of my head, and then I will start performing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Results Can Wait]]></title>
    <link href="http://bschreck.github.io/blog/2013/05/19/results-can-wait/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-19T14:49:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bschreck.github.io/blog/2013/05/19/results-can-wait</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Results don&rsquo;t show it</p>

<p>But I know I gave it all this season.</p>

<p>Why else would I get sad when I realize I have to do it all over again?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I think about all the shit that needs to happen from now till the time when I can express outwardly what I will have been preparing for and I just want to be at the end state for a while.
It&rsquo;s hard to imagine going through everything again.</p>

<p>This was a good season. Every day I came out with a purpose. Everyday I knew exactly what had to be done, and I did it.</p>

<p>And I did it right. I didn&rsquo;t do it for the outward success like I had previously. I did it for the inner transformation. In the end, that transformation didn&rsquo;t quite present itself outwardly like I would have liked, and like the other athletes around me were able to do. But it readied me for battle. It prepared me for life, and specifically for directing my life. What happens next is determined by me and me alone, with everyone else acting to help me out and let me live.</p>

<p>I won. I won at the only game that matters- the only game where winning means nothing. The only game where winning is never actually possible. I understand now. I can do whatever the flows around me hint is the downstream path. The disguised path of least resistance. This is not about swimming upstream, as most mental advisors, success advocates, and determined coaches will let me know. It&rsquo;s not about fighting &ldquo;the easy way&rdquo;. It&rsquo;s about discovering another, separate, much less violent or choppy path, through which I can flow silently with ease, content with every second of the ride.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
