<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Zen | Vaulting For Mu]]></title>
  <link href="http://bschreck.github.io/blog/categories/zen/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bschreck.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-09T16:07:13-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://bschreck.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ben Schreck]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[benjaminschreck93@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[About the Name]]></title>
    <link href="http://bschreck.github.io/blog/2014/01/13/about-the-name/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-13T13:13:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bschreck.github.io/blog/2014/01/13/about-the-name</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Mu is an ancient Zen concept that means “unasking a question”. It is the third answer to a yes or no question. However, it’s also understood in a broader context, representing the point at which opposites intersect or the fundamental meaning behind paradoxes. It’s best understood through Zen koans— traditional Zen stories that attempt to reveal the underlying nature of the universe through odd, simple, nonsensical stories.</p>

<p>Here’s an example:</p>

<!-- more -->


<blockquote><p>Joshu began the study of Zen when he was sixty years old and continued until he was eighty, when he realized Zen. He taught from the age of eighty until he was one hundred and twenty.</p>

<p>A student once asked him: &lsquo;If I haven’t anything in my mind, what shall I do?&rsquo;</p>

<p>Joshu replied: &lsquo;Throw it out.&rsquo;</p>

<p>&lsquo;But if I haven’t anything, how can I throw it out?&rsquo; continued the questioner.</p>

<p>‘Well,&lsquo; said Joshu, 'then carry it out.’ “</p></blockquote>

<p>Reading this as a simple parable makes no sense, and that’s the point. It is supposed to stimulate thought about the vary nature of paradox. The next logical question you should have in your mind is, “What doers this mu nonsense have to do with pole vaulting?” Well that would also be hard to just explain logically. I’ll quote one more story here, and allow you to try to understand this question by gradually reading through and following my journey as I blog about it.</p>

<p>This is my favorite Zen quote, written by a Japanese Zen master in the middle of the 20th century:</p>

<blockquote><p>To realize Zen one has to pass through the barrier of the patriarchs. Enlightenment always comes after the road of thinking is blocked. If you do not pass the barrier of the patriarchs or if your thinking road is not blocked, whatever you think, whatever you do, is like a tangling ghost. You may ask: &lsquo;What is a barrier of a patriarch?’ This one word, ‘MU’, is it.</p>

<p>This is the barrier of Zen. If you pass through it, you will see Joshu face to face. Then you can work hand in hand with the whole line of patriarchs. Is this not a pleasant thing to do?</p>

<p>If you want to pass this barrier, you must work through every bone in your body, through every pore of your skin, filled with this question: ‘What is ‘MU’?’ and carry it day and night. Do not believe it is the common negative symbol meaning nothing. It is not nothingness, the opposite of existence. If you really want to pass this barrier you should feel like drinking a hot iron ball that you can neither swallow nor spit out.</p>

<p>Then your previous lesser knowledge disappears. As a fruit ripening in season, your subjectivity and objectivity naturally become one. It is like a dumb man who has had a dream. He knows about it but he cannot tell it.</p>

<p>When he enters this condition his ego-shell is crushed and he can shake the heaven and move the earth. He is like a great warrior with a sharp sword. If a Buddha stands in his way, he will cut him down; if a patriarch offer him any obstacle, he will kill him; and he will be free in his way of birth and death. He can enter any world as if it were his own playground. I will tell you how to do this with this koan:</p>

<p>Just concentrate your whole energy into this MU, and do not allow any discontinuation. When you enter this MU and there is no discontinuation, your attainment will be as a candle burning and illuminating the whole universe.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zen and the Art of PV: A Summary of My Pole Vault Career]]></title>
    <link href="http://bschreck.github.io/blog/2013/04/29/zen-and-the-art-of-pv-a-summary-of-my-pole-vault-career/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-29T14:20:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bschreck.github.io/blog/2013/04/29/zen-and-the-art-of-pv-a-summary-of-my-pole-vault-career</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I put the finishing touches on the solution to the hardest problem I have ever faced. I&rsquo;ve known about this problem for the last four and a half years, and have been trying to solve it since day one. It&rsquo;s driven me far deeper into the sport of pole vaulting than I would have ever imagined I&rsquo;d be capable of. The sheer number of hours dedicated to understanding and overcoming the problem is far more than I believe most people ever dedicate to a single entity, and the variance and intensity of the emotions I&rsquo;ve experienced as a result of it over the last 5 years has taken me on a ridiculous roller coaster ride that seems so far removed from my otherwise average upbringing.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In 10th grade, I had a rare, but certainly not wholly unexpected, sunscreen-related pole vault accident. I had applied sunscreen before practice, but had forgotten to wash my hands. When I tried to jump and take off the ground holding the pole, I couldn&rsquo;t maintain my grip and so I slipped off. The fiber glass pole was already bent from the pressure I had exerted with my arms, and so it rebounded against my knee. I was hurt pretty bad for an hour or so. But as a young, fearless pole vaulter with no history of accidents, I was able to get back on the runway later that day and easily take a few more jumps. It was a scary accident, but this was a scary sport and more than anything else it served to demonstrate that one of the most frightening incidents was not all that dangerous.</p>

<p>But my mind never really processed it to completion. An idea was implanted deep into the more primitive aspects of my mind that this sport was dangerous. I unconsciously attributed two reasons why this event occurred, in order to keep myself safe in the future. The obvious and correct one, that sunscreen compromised my grip in a freak accident, became the weaker of the two. The stronger one would come to haunt me for years. I came to believe that my grip strength was not sufficient, or was only barely sufficient, and that minuscule changes in the tape job, or the weather conditions, or how sticky my hands were that day directly affected my ability to hold on to the pole. So I stopped taking off the ground. I simply could not do it. I was a paralyzed pole vaulter who could not pole vault.</p>

<p>I began to refer to this inability to take off as the &ldquo;problem&rdquo;, or simply as &ldquo;it&rdquo;. &ldquo;It&rdquo; became the most frustrating part of my life for almost 5 years. In other writings, I have described in detail the various stories, triumphs, breakthroughs, losses, and expenses that occurred because of it, and so here I will only focus on the ultimate solution.</p>

<p>By the end of my freshman year of college, my coach helped me realize that in order to fix my problem, I would have to dig deep into my mind. It would be a journey. In fact, I would come to recognize that the whole time it had been a journey, albeit mostly an unconscious one prior to this point. Instead of trying to find out what was wrong with, or just demanding to myself that I needed to &ldquo;man up&rdquo;, I would have to confront the root cause of the problem, fully understand it, and gradually diminish its effects. I began to read all kinds of books on Eastern philosophy and began practicing meditation. I started to understand that in order to fix the problem, I would need to control my head. So I stopped getting frustrated when things didn&rsquo;t go according to plan. This was an extremely difficult task in and of itself, and after a year I have still have my occasional bouts of frustration, mostly pertaining to school and stress. But I&rsquo;m much, much better than I used to be, and I no longer succumb to anger or frustration during practice. I&rsquo;m able to sense my mental state changing for the worse before it holds me hostage, and can quickly reset to avoid trouble. This mind-control seemed like the solution for about 6 months- throughout the summer and into the fall of my sophomore year. I didn&rsquo;t have the problem once. However, &ldquo;it&rdquo; had never really began it&rsquo;s hold on me until January, and so just like every other year, it came back right when I arrived at MIT after winter break. It started with a little glitch. I went back to a 5-step from a 4 (pole-vaulter lingo- 4-step means 4 lefts away from the pit, or 8 steps. 5-step means 5 lefts or 10 steps), and felt slightly off. I became exceedingly conscious of my run, and could no longer take off. And this glitch persisted, and gradually developed into the full blown &ldquo;problem&rdquo;.</p>

<p>However, this time around I had the machinery to deal with it. I was extremely annoyed and confused at first, because I thought I had gotten rid of it for good. But then I accepted that it had come back and I would have to deal with it. I no longer got frustrated at practice. I kept my cool and began trying everything I had tried in the past to combat it. After about a month without much luck, I realized that my old techniques were not working, and didn&rsquo;t represent the full solution I was working towards. One day, I was fed up, depressed, and almost broke my nearly perfect composure at practice. I realized that this problem can&rsquo;t be unique to me, or even to my sport. So I switched to the other side of my brain, took out my laptop, and consulted the world&rsquo;s most trusted resource. I had researched this problem before; I had read 5 or 6 sports psychology books, and even consulted 3 different psychologists the summer before college who I didn&rsquo;t fully trust or really give enough time to see any benefit (I was also ashamed of using my parents money for what I perceived as a stupid problem). This time though, I was determined to find an underlying reason, and knew that it existed. Somehow I stumbled across a new school of sports psychology that claimed to solve this exact problem for many different athletes at all levels of play. They claimed that standard coaching methods simply do not work for these RSPP&rsquo;s (repetitive sports performance problems) because in reality they are a form of post-traumatic stress syndrome, and must be treated as such. I began to dig around more and more, experimenting with some ad-hoc techniques I found on youtube that claimed to treat PTSD, and then eventually bought a book. I think I read it in 2 days, which is no easy task on an MIT student&rsquo;s schedule.</p>

<p>The basic theory is that past trauma is not fully processed, and
triggers a flight/fight/freeze response unconsciously when stimulated by
putting oneself in a similar environment. I realize that every time I
pole vaulted, or even though about pole vaulting, a feeling of anxiety
would overwhelm me and cloud my thoughts. I still had not come to grips
with my high school incidents where I slipped off the pole. In order to
deal with this, I needed to allow my brain to process the events, and
realize that they were nothing to be concerned with. The psychologists
who had written the book had come up with a technique they call
&ldquo;brain-spotting&rdquo;, which consisted of fixating the eye on a particular
spot in the patient&rsquo;s field of vision that would trigger the stressful
reaction. Once this spot was found, the patient would relax and let
their mind/sub-conscious process the event. This is a form of EMDR
(Eye-Movement Desensitization and Reprocessing), the technique used for
treating PTSD. I found a way to practice this on my own, and began noticing a difference in the way I visualized and thought about pole vault. I also consulted a psychologist who specialized in this treatment, but only a single time since I believed I could do it on my own, and I didn&rsquo;t want to pay for it.</p>

<p>While I began to believe that the brain-spotting would solve the issue of unprocessed trauma, it soon became clear that this was not the complete solution. I would fall back into my old habits easily, and the problem would come and go seemingly randomly. I began to experiment more and more with different techniques, including many new ones I made up myself, and for another month I accrued more and more thoughts, techniques, feelings, and emotions in my head during practice until finally one day my coach confronted me. He asked me a question that he asks me a lot: &ldquo;What are you thinking?&rdquo; I told him that there was a sea of negative thoughts floating around in my mind and I was desperately struggling to stay afloat. He thought for a minute, and told me to walk away, clear everything out of my head, and then come back. At that moment, we seemed to share a spark of insight.</p>

<p>I walked about 30 feet away, sat down, and meditated for 10-15 minutes.
When I came back, Patrick, my coach, began to instruct in the proper way
to pole vault:</p>

<p>&ldquo;Ben, today we are going to learn how to pole vault. This
is going to be a difficult endeavor, but if you follow everything I say
you will be both safe and successful. I want you to grab this pole, hold
here, take 3 big steps back from the box, take note of that mark, step
back from the runway and visualize yourself running 3 steps and then
jumping off the ground with the pole. Then proceed to the mark that your
remembered, and do exactly what you visualized in your head. Then come
see me.&rdquo;</p>

<p>I did this, and in my mind I was just learning how to pole vault again.
I was a novice, with no habits, and I simply followed what my coach told
me to do in a purely mechanical way. Obviously this wasn&rsquo;t entirely
accurate- I still knew how to pole vault, and the whole act required
my body to remember the habits involved in knowing which muscles to use
when. However, in my head it made perfect sense that I was new to this.
I needed to relearn everything. And it started working. I took that jump
no problem, then walked over to Patrick to receive my next instruction.</p>

<p>&ldquo;Good job, Ben. Now, I want you to listen to what I tell you. Today we
are going to learn how to pole vault. This is going to be a difficult
endeavor, but if you follow everything I say&hellip;&rdquo;</p>

<p>And he repeated the same thing he had said before, and I repeated the
same thing I did before. This went on for a few more jumps, and he
gradually told me to do more and more things related to actually pole
vaulting. We continued this style of coaching for a couple weeks, until
I started internalizing it, and learning how to focus, and how to trust
my coach and myself.</p>

<p>Even though this new beginning worked incredibly well from my 3 step, when I went back to 4 the problem came back. However, it was incredibly clear now. My head was utterly empty up to the point when I stepped on the runway and grabbed the pole. Suddenly the problem revealed itself. I could turn it off and on. I could finally examine it in its full glory. I began the process of debugging my mind. First I simply observed it, and tried to get a handle on exactly when and why it showed itself. I determined that the root of the problem still lay with my grip in my right hand. Since I was able to take off on a small pole, I started off on that, and began to experiment with my grip. I changed the tape job after every job, and demonstrated to myself that nothing about my grip actually mattered. I literally peeled old, disgusting tape off of other poles and put it around the place where I held the pole, and still took off easily. I worked my way up to reasonably sized poles. This seemed like the end of it. But occasionally it crept back. I had one amazing meet, vaulting from my 3-step, which is so short that it is not even considered a true approach. Then the next meet I tried vaulting from 4, and failed miserably. I thought about why I had failed to jump, realized it was probably the stress of the meet, and spent the next two days making myself believe that pole vaulting was easy, and that I would have an amazing practice where I would take off the ground no problem. And it happened. And I started believing it more and more. I remembered how easy pole vaulting was.</p>

<p>Starting a few weeks before this I had begun reading a book called &ldquo;The Power of Habit&rdquo;. As the trauma aspect of my problem faded more and more into the distance, I began to realize that this trauma was really only half of the problem. And the reason it was so persistent even when the trauma was so removed from my mind lay in another fundamental aspect of human nature: habits. I had a habit of running through, an addiction. And I realized I was using the same cues to trigger both the nasty &ldquo;problem&rdquo; habit as well as the habit I wanted: actually pole vaulting. I started to notice these habits all the time, even when I wasn&rsquo;t vaulting. I could conjure them up in mental visualizations. They revolved around the same event, yet were distinct. One ended up with me either not being able to hold the pole, or not being strong enough to power the pole into the pit. In the other, I was much larger than the pole, easily bent it, and took a fantastic vault. I worked to make the good habit stronger than the bad, since I knew I couldn&rsquo;t permanently get rid of it.</p>

<p>This began to work. I started to believe I was a great pole vaulter again, and then I started doing something I had never done. I started to trivialize the sport. I started to believe it was easy. And I started vaulting really well. The thursday after that last meet where I tried to vault from 4 but no-heighted, I went back to a 5-step, and got on a fairly large pole. At the end I took a jump at a 14 foot bar, and easily skied it by a foot and a half. 14 had been fairly easy for me since my senior year of high school, but I could probably count on my right hand the times I had cleared anything higher. After that day the belief that I was really good at the sport finally seemed outwardly tangible. It had always been there, but I had always believed I was jumping far lower than my capabilities, and had been trying to prove myself for years. Now my mental abilities were finally catching up to my physical abilities, and I grew more and more confident. The next practice I cleared 15'3" easily, and the one after that I went back to my 6 step and got on even bigger poles. I started clearing 16 ft bungies. However, there were still a couple hiccups that I was determined to iron out. At the championship meet the following weekend, I only jumped 14 ft because I &ldquo;bailed out&rdquo; on too many jumps, meaning I took off, but didn&rsquo;t commit to a full pole vault. On my last attempt at 14'6", I hesitated and stopped the jump early and just barely knocked the bar off, even though my hips were a foot and a half over it.</p>

<p>I became so excited to pole vault I could not concentrate on my school work. At practice on Monday, I started on the biggest pole I&rsquo;ve ever been on, but after a few jumps I started running through again. I went through my usual routine to refocus myself and start vaulting again, but it didn&rsquo;t seem to work this time. And then I realized why it wasn&rsquo;t working. I was using the same cues that led to my run-through habit. At this point, I decided that coming up with new cues would take a lot of work, and it was championship season, so I would put it off to next year. I instead decided to refocus and think about how easy it was to pole vault the last couple of weeks. I got back on the runway, laughed, thought about the triviality of it all, cleared my mind, visualized the jump, then stepped forward and took an amazing vault. When I walked off the pit I had one of those rare &ldquo;Eureka&rdquo; moments. I realized that the reason I had been vaulting so well was precisely because I had invented a new routine. I had come up with new cues, which triggered the good habit and let me vault well. I realized that, almost without fail, all the times I had taken off the ground had started with this new routine. It was as if my body and mind had unconsciously solved my problem for me. All I had to do now was clear my mind, believe whole-heartedly that pole-vaulting was easy, laugh a little, visualize, clear my head, step back on the runway behind my step, and then slowly walk up to my mark. Previously, my routine had consisted of me stepping onto the runway from the side, and not laughing or smiling. This new routine was different enough to launch myself into the new habit.</p>

<p>The old habit is still there, as well as a few other small tweaks that will occasionally prevent me from taking off. These include &ldquo;choking&rdquo;, where I become conscious of my run or my grip during the approach and break away from the good habit. However, I am 1000% confident in my ability to pole vault well, and the deep understanding of and familiarity with my mind I now have is already helping me succeed in all other areas of my life. My confidence is on a steadily upward slope, and coming out of this I feel like I can solve any problem given enough time. The whole process is the single most defining aspect of my mental growth and maturity over the past 5 years, even more so than MIT or my first long-term girlfriend. And although I believe I have completely characterized the problem, I also know that old habits never die, so I will need to constantly be on my toes to prevent them from exerting any influence on my life. The mental toolkit I have built to solve this problem will also stay with me for the rest of my life, and I know I will never succumb to habits, trauma, depression, or any tough situation. I plan on vaulting at least throughout college, and have set my goals high. Never mind if I actually accomplish all of them, because I have already accomplished the biggest one, and I love the process just as much as the end result. That being said, I do love winning, and nationals is right around the corner.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
